<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly and learned sermon, vpon the 91. psalme Declaring how, and to what place, a Christian man ought to flie in the daungerous time of the pestilence, for his best safetie and deliuerance. By T.C. VVher-unto are ioyned, certaine fruitfull prayers, very necessarie for the time of infection.</title>
            <author>T. C., fl. 1603.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852584</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17911</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17911)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1228:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly and learned sermon, vpon the 91. psalme Declaring how, and to what place, a Christian man ought to flie in the daungerous time of the pestilence, for his best safetie and deliuerance. By T.C. VVher-unto are ioyned, certaine fruitfull prayers, very necessarie for the time of infection.</title>
                  <author>T. C., fl. 1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for Edward White, dwelling neere the little north doore of S. Pauls Church, at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XCI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> GODLY AND <hi>LEARNED SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON,</hi> VPON THE 91. Pſalme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Declaring how, and to what</hi> place, a Chriſtian man ought to <hi>flie in the daungerous time of the</hi> Peſtilence, for his beſt ſafetie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By T. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVher-unto are ioyned, certaine</hi> fruitfull Prayers, very neceſſarie for the time of infection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for Edward White, dwelling neere the little North doore of S. Pauls <hi>Church, at the ſigne of the Gun.</hi> 1603.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A godly and learned Sermon</hi> vpon the 91. Pſalme.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shewing howe, and to what place, a</hi> Chriſtian man ought to flie in the dangerous time of the Peſtilence, for his beſt ſafetie and deliuerance.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or-as-much as Almightie God, doth now viſite, handle &amp; puniſh this country and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with the horrible and fearefull plague of the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and many folkes (after an vnmanerly faſhion) are ſo affraide there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that there bee heard and ſéene of them almanner of vnaccuſtomable woordes and workes, which become not well a Chriſtian man: And ſeeing that all the déedes of charitie which one Chriſtian man is bound to ſhewe vnto another (no leſſe then vnto Chriſt him ſelfe) are perilouſly omitted,
<pb facs="tcp:17911:3"/> whereby then riſeth all manner of ſlaunder to the weake, and miſreport vnto the holy Goſpell: I thought it profitable and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to beſtow vpon your charitie in this caſe, a ſhort inſtruction &amp; comfort out of the holy Scripture, to the intent, that the ignorant may be taught, the weake ſtrengthened, and euery one counſelled after his calling, to ſerue his neighbour.</p>
            <p>And I will take for my Text, the 91. Pſalme, which ſoundeth after this maner:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 1 Who ſo ſitteth vnder the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the higheſt, and abideth vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of the Almightie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 He ſayeth vnto the Lord: my hope, and my ſtrong holde: my God, in him will I truſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3 For hee deliuereth me from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noyſome peſtilence.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Hee ſhall couer thee with his feathers, &amp; thy truſt ſhall be vnder his winges: his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and trueth ſhall be thy ſhield and buckler.</p>
            <p n="5">5 So that thou needeſt not to feare for any terror by night, nor for the arrowes that flye by day.</p>
            <p n="6">6 For the Peſtilence that commeth priuily in the darke: nor for the ſickeneſſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth in the no one day.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb facs="tcp:17911:3"/>7 Though a thouſand fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand, yet ſhall it not come nye thee.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Yea, with thine eyes ſhalt thou ſee thy deſire, and beholde, how the vngodly ſhall be rewarded.</p>
            <p>BUt afore wee come to the vnderſtanding of theſe comfortable wordes: your charity ſhal firſt know, that it is not my meaning to forbid or inhibite any man to flye or to vſe Phyſicke, or to auoide dangerous and ſicke places in theſe fearefull ayres, ſo farre as a man doth not therein againſt the beliefe, nor Gods commandement, nor againſt his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, nor againſt the loue of his neighbour. For though ſome will ſaye: Such Plague toucheth no man, but thoſe that be ordained of God thereunto, like as there be certaine enſamples thereof found in holy Scripture: namely, as in <hi>Ezech.</hi> 9. &amp; <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7. there was ſent an Angell, which aforehand marked the vertuous and elect, or euer it was charged and commanded the ſecond Angell to ſmite (with Peſtilence or other Plagues) thoſe that were not marked. Neuertheles, againſt that it might be ſaid: Good ſir, though it went ſo at ſuch a time in ſuch places, who maketh
<pb facs="tcp:17911:4"/> vs ſure yet now, that it ſhal therfore chance ſo in al other deathes of the country? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will nowe at this time let all ſuch things continue in their libertie at your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s like as al other natural things, which bee ſubiect and committed vnto our reaſon to rule. But as for the Chriſtian which (by reaſon of office, or for pouerties ſake, or for other reaſonable cauſes) cannot, or be not minded to fly, I will herewithal ſhew them their beſt &amp; higheſt comfort that they haue.</p>
            <p>In like manner, I will not enter againſt them, that ſpeake naturally thereof, and ſay: Such Plague commeth out of the influence of the Starres, out of the working of the Cometes, out of the vnſeaſonable weather and altering of the ayre, out of the South windes, out of ſtincking waters, or out of foule miſtes of the grounde: For ſuch wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of theirs, will we leaue vnto them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſpiſed, and not fight thereagainſt: But (as Chriſtian men) we will holde vs vnto the worde of God, the ſame will we ſuffer to be our moſt high wiſedome, and giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence vnto it, and follow it: and ſo ſhall wee finde much better &amp; ſurer inſtruction: Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that this horible Plague of the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence commeth out of Gods wrath, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:17911:4"/> of the deſpiſing and tranſgreſſing of his godly commandements. For thus ſayth the holy Prophet <hi>Moyſes</hi> in the booke of <hi>Deut. Chap. 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 1. If thou wilt not hearken vnto the voyce of the Lorde thy GOD, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and keepe all his commaundements and ordinances which I commaunde thee, then ſhall all theſe curſes come vppon thee, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 21. The Lorde ſhall cauſe the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to endure long with thee:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22. The Lorde ſhall ſmire thee with ſwelling, Feauer, heate, burning, blaſting, drouth, &amp;c. And ſhall perſecute thee till hee vtterly deſtroy thee, and bring thee to naught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And certainely this is the plaine trueth, and the very originall of theſe Plagues. No man ought to doubt thereon: For though the foreſaide naturall cauſes doe ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée alſo thereunto, yet is it ſure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, that the ſame cauſes bee ſent and ſtirred vp out of Gods wrath for our ſinne and vnthankefulneſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:5"/>
            <p>And truely, that it is euen ſo; the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture declareth; not with bare wordes onely, but ſheweth it alſo with notable enſamples. For in the fourtéenth chapter of the book of <hi>Numbers,</hi> when all the ſpyes (except <hi>Ioſua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi>) ſpake euill of the lande of promiſe, and made the people vnpatient &amp; in an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore: ſo that they choſe them a Captaine, and thought to goe againe into Egypt, and to ſtone <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> which commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them the contrary, we read thus: <hi>Then appeared the glory of the Lord, and ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moyſes;</hi> How long doth this people blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheame me? And how long wil it be yer they beleeue me, for al the tokens that I haue done vpon them? therefore will I ſmite and deſtroy them with Peſtilence, and make of thee a greater nation then this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe alſo when <hi>Dauid</hi> cauſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be numbred, againſt Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, he diſpleaſed the Lord God horribly therewith. Therefore layed he the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, ſo that he was faine to chooſe himſelfe, whether he had rather haue ſeauen yeares dearth, or thrée Moneths miſchance in battaile, or thrée dayes Peſtilence in the Lande? And when he choſe the Peſtilence, there dyed in thrée daies, ſeauenty thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:17911:5"/> men, as it is written in the laſt chapter of the ſecond booke of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Séeing then that out of the word of God, wee knowe the very cauſe of this horrible Plague: Namely, that it is the faulte of our ſinnes; as vnbeliefe, diſobedience and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulnes. Therefore, before all things, it ſhall be neceſſary, that wee refraine from the ſame; repent and amende our liues, if wee will bee preſerued and deliuered from this horrible Plague. For if God puniſh vs, becauſe of ſinne: it is good to conſider that we muſt firſt acknowledge and eſchewe our ſinnes, in caſe that hee ſhall withdrawe and take away his wrath &amp; ſharp puniſhment from vs. For if we continue in our euill, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and culpable life, certainely he will not ceaſe with the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but go foorth more and more, till he giue and recompence accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our workes. But if we knowledge our ſinne, refraine from it, repent and aſke grace, then ſhal he alſo take away his wrath. And this horrible wrath (with other heauy burthens, as warre &amp; dearth, that lye vpon our necke) ſhall hee mercifully take away from vs againe. As holy <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth, <hi>1. Cor. 11. If we iudged our ſelues, we ſhould not be iudged: But when we are iudged, wee be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened
<pb facs="tcp:17911:6"/> of the Lord, that we ſhould not bedam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the worlde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And out of all this may your charitie well perceiue, howe vnwiſely and vnchriſtianly they doe, that out of inordinate feare of this Plague, leaue their calling and office, maliciouſly withdrawing the loue, helpe, and faithfulneſſe, which they (out of Gods commaundement) are bounde to ſhewe vnto their Neighbours, and ſo doe ſin grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly againſt the commandement of God. For certainely they doe but ſtirre vp the wrath of God more earneſtly againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that hee may the ſooner take holde vpon them and plucke them away with this Plague. For men may heare on euery ſide, that ſome doe ſhunne and flye not onely the ſicke, but alſo the whole: Yea (that which is more fooliſhneſſe) euen the Platters and Candleſtickes, which come out of ſtraunge houſes, as though death did ſurely ſticke therein. And (out of ſuch fond childiſh feare) it commeth, that not onely ſome ſicke folkes bee ſuffered to die without any keeping, helpe and comforte: but that women alſo great with childe, are forſaken in their moſt néede, for at ſuch times, fewe or none will come vnto them: Yea, a man may heare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:17911:6"/> that the children forſake their Fathers and Mothers, and one houſhold body kéepeth himſelfe away from another, and ſheweth no loue vnto him: Which neuertheleſſe hee would be glad to bee ſhewed vnto himſelfe, if he lay in like neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>How be it, I ſuppoſe there come not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch chaunces to paſſe: neuertheleſſe I muſt ſpeake thereof that it be done no more from hencefoorth. For certainely it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſely and vnchriſtianly handled: and wee néede not thinke that the ſame is the waye to eſcape this Plague, but rather an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that it raigneth more mightily ouer vs. For ſéeing it is ſure (as yee haue heard afore) that ſuch Plague is ſent for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſinnes, and Chriſt hath giuen vs a newe Commandement, that we ſhould loue one another (as hee hath loued vs) it followeth that the farther we departe from the loue of our neighbour, the more wee lade ſinne vpon vs, and deſerue this plague ſo much the more.</p>
            <p>Againe, the more diligently that we take héed vnto the loue of our neighbour, the ſurer ſhall we be from this Plague: No man née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to doubt thereof.</p>
            <p>But heere withall will I alſo counſell
<pb facs="tcp:17911:7"/> or compell no man, to any vnnéedeful daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger (that he is not bound vnto by his calling nor by loue) but only warne thoſe which for feare, leaue that which they are bound to do before God: To the intent that for ſuch na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked feares ſake, they doe not tranſgreſſe nor omitte the commandement of God, &amp; hope by ſinne to eſcape this plague, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe commeth becauſe of ſinne. For that were a fooliſh vnaduiſed counſell, if one would goe about to eſcape the wrath of God by tranſgreſſion, and by ſinne to auoide the puniſhment of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, doth experience ſhewe alſo that they which bee ſo ſore afraide, doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly miſcary. Againe, they that waite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their offices and ſerue their neighbours, be deliuered; As it is well ſéene in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church, and other moe, that ſhun not the ſicke, but muſt viſite them and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them with Gods worde, and prouide for them with the holy Sacrament: For we ſée no wher, that they therfore muſt alſo be ſoone ſicke and muſt die. Yea, how muſt the higher powers of the worlde doe, which (by reaſon of their calling, and for the common profite and regiments ſake) abide alſo in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eoper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, &amp; muſt miniſter becauſe of loue? ſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:17911:7"/> the chiefeſt, of one whereof there dyeth more then a thouſand of other: And yet doth God commonly preſerue them alſo that they bee deliuered, left ſtill a liue, and dye in a good quiet age.</p>
            <p>Therefore certainely ſuch kinde of inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate feare and flying againſt Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, is nothing elſe, but a declaring of a great and ſore vnbeliefe, that men doe not beleeue &amp; truſt in God, that he can and will deliuer. And thus is verifyed the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The vngodly haue no peace. <hi>Eſa.</hi>
               </hi> lvij. For if we will feare and flye where no perrill is, when will we then beſtow our liues for our neighbours, as Chriſt hath done for vs: and we alſo be bounde to do likewiſe? 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Who ſo now deſyreth to eſcape the wrath of God, and this horrible Plague, let him not aſke his owne reaſon how hee ſhall doe, but beleeue and follow the worde of God: which teacheth him not to flye euill ayre and infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted places (which he may well do: neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hee remayneth yet vncertaine whether it helpeth or no) but it teacheth him to leaue off from ſinne, as from the very originall cauſe of this Plague and puniſhment, and (by true repentance and amendment of life) to walke againe in the right waye. For that
<pb facs="tcp:17911:8"/> is the only ſure and wholſome flying in this dangerous time, whereby a man may eſcape this Plague.</p>
            <p>But whither a man ought to flye, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will we heare the holy Ghoſt by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete in this Pſalme. He knoweth it much better then wee can thinke, and ſayeth after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. Who ſo ſitteth vnder the defence of the higheſt, and abideth vnder the ſhadow of the almightie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2 He ſayeth vnto the Lord: My hope, and my ſtrong holde: My God on whom I hope. For hee deliuereth mee from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noyſome Peſtilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe wordes (my moſt dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) ſhall yee take to hart, and marke them well with all diligence: For they be not the wordes of men which can lie and deceiue: Howbeit though they were mens wordes, and ſome olde wiſe man ſpake them (or ſome well learned Phyſitian) ye would not yet deſpiſe them, but receiue &amp; keepe them. But nowe bee they the very wordes of the high Maieſtie of God, which the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh by the mouth of the Prophete. And they teach vs whither we ought to flye
<pb facs="tcp:17911:8"/> from this Plague, that we may be ſafe. And certainely they muſt néedes bee the very truth: <hi>For heauen and earth muſt paſſe, but my words ſhall not paſſe away,</hi> ſayth the Lord.</p>
            <p>But that ye may vnderſtande them right and well, yée ſhall remember that it is the vſe of the Holy Scripture (ſpecially in the Pſalme) to declare one meaning with two manner of ſayings, as yee haue oft times heard. For ſo doeth the Prophet here ſpeake, and ſayeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſo ſitteth vnder the defence of the higheſt, and abydeth vnder the ſhaddow of the Almightie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to ſitte vnder the defence of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, is euen as much as to ſaye, as to abide vnder the ſhaddow of the almightie.</p>
            <p>And with theſe wordes meaneth the holy Prophet nothing elſe, but who ſo putteth his truſt in God with a right ſure Chriſtian beliefe, &amp; giueth himſelfe ouer into his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and defence, (for ſuch people doeth God receiue to grace) them holdeth hee for his owne deare children (&amp; euen ſo they be) &amp; giueth them his holy ſpirit, which worketh in them true ſaluation and godly workes.</p>
            <p>Therefore remayneth he alſo vpon them, and all things muſt ſerue for their wealth
<pb facs="tcp:17911:9"/> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Rom. 8.</hi> Such protection alſo and defence of God, is ſet forth vnto vs eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in the Scripture, as an ouer-ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing and couering with wings. For like as the two Cherubins ſpred out their wings ouer the Arke; <hi>Exod.</hi> 37. Euen ſo doeth God ſpred out the winges of his protection ouer his elect. Therefore ſayth <hi>Moſes <hi>Deut. 32. Like as an Egle ſtirreth vp his neſt, and flyeth ouer his yong ones: ſo ſpreadeth he out his fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and beares his people vpon his winges:</hi>
               </hi> After this maner ſpake the holy Angel <hi>Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> alſo vnto the moſt bleſſed and pure Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> when ſhe ſhould be the Mother of God: <hi>The holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon thee, and the power of the moſt higheſt ſhall ouer ſhaddow thee. <hi>Luc.</hi>
               </hi> 1. In like maner ſpake Chriſt alſo vnto Ieruſalem: <hi>How oft would I haue gathered thy Children together, as an Henne gathereth her Chickens vnder her wings, and ye would not. Mat. 23.</hi> For though a true beleeuing man be in déede the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and God dwelleth in him, yet v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Scripture oft to ſpeake thereof, as though he did flye aboue vs, in as much as he doth ouer ſhaddow, couer and defend vs? and that becauſe the heauen and the heauen of all heauens (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayeth) <hi>can not
<pb facs="tcp:17911:9"/> comprehend nor containe him. Reuel. 3.</hi> But though he dwelleth in vs, yet flyeth he wide, hye and lowe, not only on the out ſide of vs, but alſo on the outſide &amp; ouer all creatures. And ſo in all theſe wordes, there is nothing elſe ſaide, but whoſoeuer is a right beléeuing Chriſtian:</p>
            <p>Marke now then that he ſayeth not: who ſo is wiſe, ſtrong, rich, whole, or well frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Neither ſaith hee alſo: who ſo kéepeth him ſelfe thence, or flyeth thether, holdeth himſelfe wel, or vſeth good Phiſicke: but who ſo putteth his truſt in God. Not that the foreſaid good things be euill, or may not be had or vſed with profite: But that they (where fayth is not) may euen as ſoone doe harme as good, and are in no wiſe able to deliuere from the wrath of God. But what doeth the beléeuer? He ſayeth vnto the Lorde: <hi>My hope.</hi> But this do not the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnbeléeuers, but ſet their hope in the foreſaid points, put their truſt in them, and boaſt thereon, &amp; ſo commit ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome therewith, and make Idols thereof. But to God doe they not lift vp their eyes, neither thinke they vpon him, nor feare him. And when he commeth then with his wrath and ouertaketh them with his Plague, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:17911:10"/> that of neceſſitie they muſt needes thinke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, then feare they, and be afrayde of him; flie away, and knowe not where to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide: Then vaniſheth away their hope and boaſting, which they (in time of proſperitie) had vnto the creatures. And ſo commeth it to paſſe, that their wiſedome hath bene plaine fooliſhnes: their ſtrength, their owne miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: their riches, their owne deſtruction: their health, their own harme: their friends, their owne hypocrites, and traitours. And al that which they truſted vnto, cannot helpe them. When they would hide themſelues on the backſide thereof, it is euen as much as when one hideth him behinde a ladder. And when they would ſéeke helpe therby, if is euen like as a Wolfe ſhould defende a Sheepe or a Gooſe.</p>
            <p>But thus goeth it not with the beleeuer: for who ſo putteth his truſt in the Lorde, ſhall not be confounded. Therefore ſaith he not onely that the Lord is his hope but alſo his ſtrong holde, which he may flie vnto, in the which he may ſhut him ſelfe cloſe, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered therein. As <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayeth in the xviii. Chapter of the Prouerbes: <hi>The name of the Lord is a ſtrong Caſtell, the righteous flyeth vnto it, and ſhall bee defended.</hi> For
<pb facs="tcp:17911:10"/> the vnbeleeuers haue their hope euen in their goodes, but in neceſſitie, they finde no refuge, as the faithfull hath a ſtrong holde and high Caſtell in GOD the Lorde.</p>
            <p>And though the vnbeleeuers haue their whole will all their life long, yet hath it an euill ende, as it had with the rich man, which was buried in hell. <hi>Luke</hi> Chapter xvi. For who ſo beléeueth not, ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Againe, though the faithfull be plagued and perſecuted all his life long, ſo that hee can not ſée howe hee may be deliuered, yet hath hee this comfort, that the Lord is his God: that is, that he can helpe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him as an almightie Lorde, yea, after ſuch a faſhion and way, as neither he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe nor any mans reaſon can thinke or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe.</p>
            <p>And though he doe it not, yet doeth not the faithfull deſpaire: but letteth the Lorde be his <hi>God,</hi> on whom hee <hi>hopeth:</hi> that is, at whoſe hande he looketh for all good in the life for to come and euerlaſting. For hope ſeeth and looketh on that which is to come, which as yet is hid. As <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> the viii. Chapt. <hi>Hope that is ſeene is no hope.
<pb facs="tcp:17911:11"/> for howe can a man hope for that which is ſeene. But if wee hope for that which wee ſee not, we looke for it by patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo this is the meaning: The vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuers haue their hope in the creatures, and are afraide of God. The faithfull hath his <hi>hope</hi> to God, and is Lord ouer the creatures. The vnbeléeuers miſcarie, and by the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures finde they no helpe in néede. The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miſcarie not, but God is vnto them <hi>a ſtrong holde.</hi> The vnbeleeuers may well haue their willes as long as they liue, but at the laſt (thorow their deſpaire) there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euerlaſting damnation. The faithfull may haue diſquietneſſe and temptation all their life long, but at the laſt (thorow their hope) there followeth euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>Such hope ſhould they haue, and they haue it indeede, that though they muſt lie vnder as long as they liue, yet after death they ſhall inherite euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>But certainely it commeth not to paſſe, that they muſt alway lye vnder: For <hi>God is faithfull, and ſuffereth not his to be tempted aboue their ſtrength, but maketh the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo to haue an ende, that we may beare it.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Therefore ſayeth the Prophete moreouer:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For hee deliuereth mee from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noyſome Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in theſe words, doth he ſhortly ſhew vnto vs, that almightie God can and will deliuer his owne from all miſ-fortune, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this life. For all the miſchaunces that we be troubled withall in this temporal life, are of two ſortes: Some come out of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deuiſe of the Deuill, and of men: as ſhame and perſecution. Some plainely of nature, and out of the ordinance of God: as Tempeſt and Peſtilence. The faithfull now beleeueth and maketh his boaſte, that theſe miſchaunces can not be ſo great and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but GOD ſhall deliuer him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</p>
            <p>And it is a goodly natural ſimilitude, that he likeneth the euil wicked deuice of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly againſt the faithfull, to a nette or ſnare of the hunter. For like as a hunterproueth the kinde and nature of euery wilde beaſt, commeth priuily after him, ſeeketh out the courſe and habitation therof, and afterward ſetteth the Nette, that he may driue it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into: Euen ſo do the vngodly alſo vnto the righteous. Firſt, they looke howe they bee minded: If any one be free of language, then
<pb facs="tcp:17911:12"/> ſet they him on fire, that he may ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſharpely, as Saint <hi>Ste euen</hi> did. <hi>Actes</hi> the vij. Chapter. If he be gentle and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then imagine they ſome fooliſh thing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, and flatter away his harte from him as <hi>Dalila</hi> did vnto <hi>Sampſon.</hi> If he ſéeke the ſaluation of the people, then ſclaunder they him, as the Iewes blaſpheamed Chriſt to be a Wine-ſupper, and a companion of Publicanes. If he be ſimple, then lye they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, behinde his backe, or euer he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thereof: Then follow they vpon him, cry, lye, and complaine, that the vertuous Chriſtian man knoweth not what poynt to be at or how he hath deſerued it. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, they thinke the Bell is ſo caſt, that at the laſt it muſt ring as they will, but if fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them.</p>
            <p>For the Lord on whom we beleeue, which is our <hi>hope, refuge</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> can not onely preſerue vs from their ſnares that wee fall not therein, but alſo when we fal into them, and they thinke wee be their captiues, hee can and will deliuer vs yet thereout. In like manner doeth God the Lorde preſerue his faithfull, not onely from the noyſome ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Peſtilence, but alſo when they bee taken therewith and infected already,
<pb facs="tcp:17911:12"/> he deliuereth them from it, and maketh them whole againe. But howe that commeth to paſſe, and how we ſhal vnderſtand it, it ſhal follow hereafter more clearely.</p>
            <p>This is now well to be marked alſo, that the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> is a noyſome ſickeneſſe, not becauſe it bringeth death (for that doe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mortall ſickeneſſes likewiſe, and death is no loſſe vnto the faithfull, but <hi>aduantage,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> the firſt Chapiter) but becauſe that it taketh away the people very ſuddenly, vnlooked for and vnawares: And thereout then followeth ſtrife, lawing or buſineſſe among ſinners, and of the common wealth, as euery man by him ſelfe can lightly perceiue and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is alſo an horrible puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer the ſinne of the worlde, which concerneth both them that dye, and them that are left aliue, as hereafter it ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>Where as if there be now ſuch a fayth as gieueth credence vnto God, hee ſhal preſerue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al wicked imaginations of men, like wiſe from all noyſome ſickneſſes. And at the laſt ſhall hee ſaue him, that continueth not without fruit, but breaketh out with right
<pb facs="tcp:17911:13"/> loue and faithfulneſſe towardes his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp; deſireth alſo to bring him vnto that point, that he may beléeue and be pertaker of all ſuch goodnes and benefites of God. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the Prophete turne his words now alſo vnto his neighbour, and ſaith further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee ſhall couer thee with his fethers, and thine hope ſhall be vnder his wings.</hi> That is: if thou alſo wilt put thy truſt in him, thou ſhalt finde it ſo likewiſe. For hee ſheweth ſuch his benefits vnto all and euery one that put their truſt in him As for the <hi>couering of his fethers, and hope vnder his wings,</hi> your charitie hath heard ynough before what it is.</p>
            <p>Now, though all the faithful look for ſuch help at God, &amp; it happeneth vnto them, yet is it not done without a ſpeciall battaile of Faith. For ſuch help doth he promiſe vs in his holy word, that we ſhould beléeue it: and if we beléeue it, it happeneth vnto vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Faith. Therefore ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete moreouer, <hi>His truth is ſpeare &amp; ſhield,</hi> that is, his godly promiſes, which are ſure &amp; true, and neither lie nor deceane: Thoſe are our weapons wherewith we fight, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all aduerſities. But like as ſpeare and ſhield are not profitable vnto him that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not,
<pb facs="tcp:17911:13"/> or will not vſe them: euen ſo alſo doe not the promiſes of God profite him, that cannot fight therewith, and will not beléeue theron. For that is the right ſcience in this battaile, when miſ-fortune, aduerſity, or tentation commeth, that we looke out all for accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto Gods word: Namely, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and promiſe he hath made vnto vs in ſuch a caſe, and with a right beliefe to take holde of the ſame, as of a ſhield, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and defend our ſelues therewith: ſo can there no miſchance doe vs harme, as the holy Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the laſt chapter of his epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> teacheth, and ſaith: <hi>Before al things take the ſhield of Faith, where with ye may quench all the fierie darts of the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt the ſame (namely againſt Sathan our head enemy) is ſuch word of God, euen the right ſpeare, wherewith wee wound and ouercome him. For no bodily weapon hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and hindreth men ſo ſore, as the word of God ſtoppeth and hindreth Sathan, if it bee thruſt vnder his noſe, againſt his venemous dealing and tentation, For if a ſeruant (that dealeth wrongfully and vnthriftily in his maiſters goods and buſineſſes) be affraide, vexed, and pearſed through the hart, when a ſimple man ſaith vnto him: Thou vnthrift,
<pb facs="tcp:17911:14"/> why doeſt thou ſo? That is not thy maiſters will and meaning, he did not ſo commaund thée. How much more goeth it thorow Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans hart, when a vertuous Chriſtian man holdeth the worde of God vnder his eyes, and bringeth witneſſe ouer him that he as a wicked creature dealeth againſt his maker, and againſt his choſen children? Therefore doeth holy Saint <hi>Paul</hi> call Gods word alſo <hi>the ſword of the ſpirit:</hi> And the Lord Chriſt defendeth himſelfe onely with the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all temptations of Sathan in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe.</p>
            <p>Nowe when thou takeſt holde thus of Gods promiſes thorow-faith, and vſeſt them for ſpeare and ſhielde to defende thy ſelfe, and to ſmite Sathan, then out of the ſame, it followeth, as the Prophete ſayeth far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thou needeſt not to feare for the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribleneſſe of the night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the arrowes that flye in the daye time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Peſtilence that commeth priuily in the darke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the ſickeneſſe that deſtroyeth in the noone day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For theſe foure aduerſities ſet forward
<pb facs="tcp:17911:14"/> and ſhorten the life of the vnbeléeuers: But the faithfull hath ſuch conſolation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that he néedeth not be afraide. Firſt, for the horribleneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night: That is, for al manner of temptation &amp; deceite, that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vnto men by night in the darkneſſe. For this we al perceiue, that in the night &amp; in the darkeneſſe wee are weaker minded, of more diſpaire, and more afraid then in the light.</p>
            <p>The bloud runneth to our hearts, and the haires ſtand vpright, and all the body wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth colde for feare. Out of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it then, that wethinke we ſée, heare, and perceiue ſomewhat, which in very deede is not ſo: then goeth one aſtray, another lée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his colour, the thirde falleth ſicke, the fourth is become crooked: the fift goeth out of his witte: And ſo men thinke that the Deuill hath done it, where as it is yet a plaine naturall woorking of the excéeding great feare, which would deſtroye a man euen by daye time, if it were ſo greate.</p>
            <p>How-be-it, true it is that the Deuill cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch feare, and printeth it in, that hee may beguyle and deſtroy vs by feare, as by a naturall working. Yet is it nothing but a feare: for the Prophet calleth it not an euil or good ſpirit, but plainely the horriblenes of the
<pb facs="tcp:17911:15"/> night: Neither is it any thing elſe but an horrour and feare, and continueth an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and and feare.</p>
            <p>Therefore where a right beliefe is, there is no feare. Where no fearefulnes is, there is alſo no horrour, nor fantaſie of ſpirites or deceitfulnes of the night, but plaine courage and boldneſſe. If any thing els be ſéene (as fire or light) they be but naturall things, out of the heat of the ground: like as lightnings, dragons, falling ſtarres and Cometes, be in the aire and in the heauen. But herewithal will not I ſpeake againſt the wonderfull vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and tokens, which God ſendeth for a warning before great miſchaunces to come.</p>
            <p>Secondarliye the faithfull is ſure <hi>for the arrowes that flie in the day time.</hi> That is all manner of miſchaunces, which ouertake a man openly in the daye: and yet ſo ſuddenly and vnwares, that he can not eſcape them. As when a tyle falleth from the rooofe of an houſe, when a wicked beaſt doeth euill, or when an vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grations perſon doth hurt in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, traine, or goods. For ſuch miſfortunes come for the moſt part ſo ſuddenly, that a man can not preuent them, but muſt let them hitte as with an arrow, and afterward reſtore and heale the harme with great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle
<pb facs="tcp:17911:15"/> and labour. But now will God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his faithfull from ſuch miſfortune<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if they haue his promiſes before their eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue thereon, and order their liues thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a faithfull perſon needeth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be afrayde for the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> that flip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth <hi>in priuilie in the darke.</hi> This is verily a comfortable promiſe in this dangerous time, for the which, wee ſhould by right put our truſt in God, and thanke him therefore, for aſmuch as it is one of the moſt perilous and horrible Plagues, wherewith hee viſiteth &amp; puniſheth the ſinne of the world. For it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth holde of life vnwares, and plucketh a man a way in two or three dayes (or euer he can order his buſyneſſe and houſe, and make his Teſtament) créepeth in priuily in the darke, ſo that no man knoweth what it is, or whence it commeth, or whether it goeth, therefore can no man kéepe himſelfe ſurely from it.</p>
            <p>For if it were in meate or drinke, it might be eſchued: If it were an euill taſt, it might be expelled with a ſweet ſauour: If it were an euil winde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber might with diligence be made cloſe therefore: If it were a cloude or miſt, it might be ſeene and auoyded: If it
<pb facs="tcp:17911:16"/> were a raine, a man might couer himſelfe for it: but nowe it is a ſecrete miſfortune that créepeth in priuily, ſo that it can neither be ſéene nor heard, neither ſmelled nor taſted, til it haue done thee harme.</p>
            <p>Therefore the more daungerous and noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome that the plague is, the better and more excellent is the promiſe, that no man ſhoulde haue cauſe to deſpaire. For how might God make vs a more excellent and fairer promiſe then that hee promiſeth to deliuer from the Peſtilence vs that be his children, and that we néede not to be affraide thereof, though <hi>a thouſand die</hi> of the ſame <hi>at our left ſide, &amp; ten thouſand at our right ſide.</hi> Yet ſhall it not reach vnto vs, if we doe but beléeue this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and let it be our ſpeare and ſhield. For if we ſo doe, then ſhal ſuch poiſoned arrowes either not hit vs at all, or elſe not wound vs to death.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God will alſo preſerue his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the ſickneſſe that deſtroyeth in the noone daye: For the noone day when the Sunne is at the ſtrongeſt, is cauſe of much heate and feuerous ſickneſſes: ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thoſe countries where the Sunne ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth hye, and commeth nye ouer mens heads.
<pb facs="tcp:17911:16"/> For great heate bringeth much ſweat, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth and altereth the bloud, cauſeth inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate drinking, and maketh that the people are glad to coole themſelues againe fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and thereout ariſeth all manner of peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diſeaſes, which are not very vnlike the ſickneſſe of the <hi>Peſtilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe, whether it be feare of the night, or arrowe of the day, whether it be Peſtilence or ſickneſſe that commeth by the euil South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde, or what plague ſoeuer, that lyeth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the world becauſe of their ſinnes, God the Lord will preſerue his faithfull therfrom or delyuer them from it. And that ſhal come to paſſe ſo certainly and ſo wonderfully, that (as the Pſalmiſt and our Prophet ſayeth,) <hi>Though a thouſand fall at thy left ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right ſide, yet ſhal it not touch thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is doubtles a louing, merciful, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and faire promiſe, whereon our hart by reaſon ſhould truſt, and chieſlie reioyce in the ſame. For he that ſpeaketh it, is only Almightie, and moſte true, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ſhoulde with reaſon giue credence vnto him.</p>
            <p>For we can do God no greater diſhonour then to diſpair in his holy word. We ought
<pb facs="tcp:17911:17"/> therefore to be much more afraide of that inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate feare then of death it ſelfe: for death can not hurt vs, in aſmuch as (we thorowe baptiſme) are graffed and buried vnto like death with Chriſt. But fearefulneſſe (which is nothing elſe but an vnbeliefe) may harme vs, and bring vs into imprudence. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my moſt dearely beloued, take theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to heart, ſtrengthen your heart, mind, and vnderſtanding therewith, and be not faynt harted. So ſhall yee proue by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that God is true, and faithfully perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that which he promiſeth.</p>
            <p>And that yee may the more eaſely beléeue it, I wil declare it vnto your charitie, by a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude how it commeth to paſſe, &amp; whence it ſpringeth, that a right faithful Chriſtian man may bee ſafe and free from all theſe Plagues: for it is good to vnderſtande, and comfortable to know.</p>
            <p>Your charitie ſéeth and prooueth daily by experience, how mighty &amp; horrible a thing the darkeneſſe of the night is. For when it falleth, it couereth all the whole world, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the colour and faſhion of all creatures, captiuateth all men and beaſtes liuing, that they muſt be ſtill and reſt, yea, and maketh them faintharted and fearefull, and ſo of all
<pb facs="tcp:17911:17"/> things it is a mighty inuincible tyraunt whom no man may withſtand. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, it is not yet ſo mighty, that it can darken, ouerwhelme, and quench the leaſt light that is founde in the world. For wee ſée, that the darker the night is, the clearer doe the ſtarres ſhine: Yea, the leaſt candle light that is lighted, withſtandeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole night, and ſuffereth not onely the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe not to couer or oppreſſe it, but giueth light euen in the middes of the darkenes, and ſmiteth it backe a certaine ſpace on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide: &amp; where it is borne, thence muſt darkeneſſe depart, and giue place vnto the light: al the power and fearefulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, can not helpe againſt it.</p>
            <p>And though a light be ſo weake, that it giueth not light farre aboue it, neither can ſmite the darkeneſſe backe (as the ſparke of an whote cole) yet can not the darkenes couer it, much leſſe quench it: but it giueth light it ſelfe alone, ſo that it may be ſéene a farre off in the darkeneſſe, and remayneth vnouercome of the ſame, though it cannot helpe other thinges, nor giue light vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to them.</p>
            <p>Yea (that yet more wonderfull is) a rotten ſhining péece of Wood, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17911:18"/> hath the faynteſt light that can be founde, remayneth inuincible of all the power of darkeneſſe: and the more it is compaſſed about with darkeneſſe, the clearer light it giueth: ſo little can darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ouercome or holde downe any light, but it ruleth, vanquiſheth, and expelleth the darkeneſſe, which elſe ouerwhelmeth, ſnareth, and putteth all things in feare.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo likewiſe doth a well ſpring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for there may we ſee, how a little vaine of water, breaketh out of the groundſome where ſcarce ſo great as a finger.</p>
            <p>And when it is cloſed in rounde about, that the water may gather together, and muſt néedes be a ditch or a pitte, yet ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it neuertheleſſe. And though the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bee certaine hundreds weight aboue the ſpring, yet may not it driue the ſpring backe, but the ſpring driueth the whole burthen of the water backe, and aboue it ſelfe, and ſpringeth ſtill more and more, till the poole flowe ouer. And if the other water be foule and vncleane, it cannot mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it ſelfe vnder the freſh cleare water of the ſpring, but it remaineth cleare till it come farther abroad from the firſt head thereof, as it may wel be prooued by daily
<pb facs="tcp:17911:18"/> experience. If a naturall light then be ſo mighty againſt the darkenes of the night, and an earthen well ſpring ſo ſtrong in ſtryuing againſt all ſtanding waters: howe much more doeth it then, the true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting and heauenly light, and the onely inuinſible ſpring of all life, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God the Lorde our maker and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our?</p>
            <p>That God is the true, euerlaſting and heauenly light, witneſſeth Iohn the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt in the firſt Chapter, and ſayeth: <hi>God was the worde, in him was the life, and the life was the light of men.</hi> Likewiſe alſo in his Canonicall Epiſtle in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: <hi>God is light, and in him is no darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, That he is the onely inuincible ſpring of all life, witneſſeth the Prophet Ieremie in the ſeconde Chapter. For there ſayth the Lord: <hi>My people committeth a double ſinne, they forſake me the liuing ſpring of life, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues fayre welles, which neuertheleſſe giue no water.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaieth in the xxxv. Pſalme: <hi>With thee is the ſpring of life, and in thy light ſee we light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If God the Lord then be the true light,
<pb facs="tcp:17911:19"/> it followeth that all they which put their truſt in him, bee as a burning candle: for by faith doth God dwell in our harts, and we are the liuing temple of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> doeth witneſſe more then once. Therefore ſaith Chriſt of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Math.</hi> 5. <hi>Ye are the light of the world.</hi> And of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt: <hi>He was a burning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhining light. <hi>Iohn</hi>
               </hi> 5. Likewiſe if God be the euerlaſting and liuing fountaine, it followeth, that the faithfull be euen flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſprings. Therefore ſayth Chriſt alſo. <hi>Iohn</hi> 7. <hi>Who ſo beleeueth on mee,</hi> as the Scripture ſayeth, <hi>out of his body ſhal flow ſtreames of liuing Water: But this he ſaide of the Spirit which they that beleeue on him ſhould receiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Like as the darkeneſſe of the night now can hurt no earthly or worldly light, but muſt giue place and flye from the light: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo ſaith Satan alſo which is a Prince of ſpirituall darkeneſſe, can doe no harme to a true right beléeuing Chriſtian man, but muſt feare and flie from him: For God which is the euerlaſting light, dwelleth &amp; ſhineth in his hart, and driueth and expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth far from him all the workes of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And like as no heape of water can
<pb facs="tcp:17911:19"/> driue backe any fountaine of the grounde, and hinder the quicke ſpring thereof: and like as no vncleanneſſe can make it foule, euen ſo alſo can no aduerſity of this world take away or ſhorten any Chriſtian mans life. For God which is the fountaine of all life, dwelleth and liueth in his heart, and driueth all hurtful poyſon and mortal ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes farre away from thence, ſo that not onely it can not harme him, but hee alſo helpeth other people, and deliuereth them by his preſence: euen as a light that ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth farre about it, and as a ſpring that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way floweth, runneth and maketh the ground moyſt and fruitfull.</p>
            <p>And this is that the Lord ſayeth in the Goſpell, in the laſt of <hi>Marke: <hi>The tokens that ſhall follow them which beleeue, are theſe: In my name ſhall they caſt out deuils, ſpeake with newe tongues, driue away ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents: and if they drinke any deadly thing, it ſhall not hurt them: They ſhall lay handes vpon the ſicke, and they ſhall recouer.</hi>
               </hi> So is it read alſo in the Actes of the Apoſtles the v. Chapter, that the ſicke were made whole onely of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſhaddow.</p>
            <p>So vtterly muſt we vaniſh euery thing that is contrary &amp; againſt the euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:17911:20"/> light and ſpringe of life, where a right Chriſtian man is, in whome God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by a true beliefe and out of whom the holy Ghoſt ſhineth and floweth.</p>
            <p>Let Satan then preſſe in here with all his darkeneſſe, and with all his hurtful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, yet ſhal ye ſee in beliefe that he can not take or deſtroy any Chriſtian man therewith, if he continue in faith, &amp; kéepe God in his hart: But he ſhall be ſmitten backe and driuen away by force, as the wounderfull workes of Chriſt, and of all Saints doe manifeſtly declare. Therefore it is a great ſhame for a chriſtian man to be afraid for the Plague of the Peſtilence, as to flye from them whome he is bounde to ſerue by Gods commaundement. For by reaſon hee ſhould without all feare make haſte vnto them, not onely to fulfill Gods commaundement, but alſo by his preſence to helpe them, if their faith doe elſe worke withall. But if it come not to paſſe, yet is hee ſure, for aſmuch as God dwelleth in him, and he walketh and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in Gods commandement. For certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this promiſe ſhall not faile him:</p>
            <p>Though a thouſand fall at thy ſide, &amp; ten thouſand at thy right ſide, yet ſhall it not
<pb facs="tcp:17911:20"/> touch thee.</p>
            <p>But with faith muſt theſe wordes be taken holde vpon, for naturall reaſon doth not comprehend them, in aſmuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede it appeareth farre otherwiſe. And no man néedeth to thinke nor iudge, that they which die of this plague, be all vnchriſtian and faithleſſe: but we ought not to doubt, but that there die thereof many vertuous men, and leaue many vngodly. This is done, becauſe that death may happen to a man two manner of waies.</p>
            <p>One way after the common courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, according as euery mans death is appointed him of God: and we haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto it in baptiſme. Of this ſayth the holy man <hi>Job</hi> in the xiiii. Chapter: <hi>A man hath his appoynted time, the number of his moneths ſtandeth with thee: thou haſt appoynted him his bounds, which hee ſhall not ouerpaſſe.</hi> Another way may death happen to a man before the time, by reaſon of his great &amp; grieuous ſinnes: As the Lord hath threatned by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> that if his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement be not kept, he wil cauſe <hi>peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> to reigne: whereout it is certain, that when they be kept, the plague abideth out. Likewiſe ſaith he in the commandements:
<pb facs="tcp:17911:21"/> 
               <hi>Honor Father and mother that thou maieſt liue long, &amp;c.</hi> Out of the which it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that his life which doeth them not, ſhall be ſhortened. In like manner ſayeth <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 55. <hi>Pſalme, The bloud-thirſtie ſhal not bring their life to the halfe nomber.</hi> Whereout it is ſure, that they ſhould liue much longer, if they ſhed not innocent blood. Likewiſe Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Luk. 12. Ifye doe not repent, yee ſhall all periſh, as they that the towre in <hi>Siloa</hi> fell vpon.</hi> Whereby it is certaine, that who ſo repenteth not, may looke for all miſ-fortune.</p>
            <p>And of this vntimely death onely ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this Pſalme, and promiſeth the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtian men, that they ſhall be frée from it. For from the right apointed death into the which we haue conſented in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, we neither can, nor ſhall be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Wherefore if a vertuous right Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man die of this plague, it is certainly his very houre appointed vnto him of God which he cannot preuent. But doubtleſſe, there dye of it many ſinners alſo beſide, which might well liue longer if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented. And though ſome bee taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their ſinnes, yet be they not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore damned, but if they aſke forgiueneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17911:21"/> of ſinnes, and beléeue, they ſhall be ſaued: As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>When wee be iudged, we are chaſtened of the Lord, that wee ſhould not be condemned with the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus goeth it then together, that iuſt men die their owne right death, but the wicked die an vntimely death, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with doeth God puniſh the world ſoreſt of all, becauſe of their ſinnes, but ſpareth his owne for their faiths ſake. Therefore ſhould they not be feareful nor faint-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but (as the Prophet ſaieth) they ſhould looke and beholde, how the vngodly are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced: For whether the wicked dye before the time, or the iuſt in the right ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet is it done both for the puniſhment and plague of the vngodly. If vertous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers die from wicked diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient children, then be the children pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: for they are afterward, euil nurtered, hanged or ſlaine. If yong children dye from wicked fathers and mothers, then be the children deliuered, and the fathers and mothers puniſhed, in that they haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered their goods for thoſe that they wiſh them not vnto. If tyraunts die, then bee they puniſhed, and the perſecuted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an deliuered. If good rulers die, which
<pb facs="tcp:17911:22"/> with their wiſdome haue maintayned peace and good gouernance, then be they in peace: And ſo the vngodly which are left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, rayſe vp warre and ſedicion, and bee alway puniſhed worſe and worſe. Shortly who ſo hath eyes of faith, ſéeth that true beleeuers die in a right ſeaſon, but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly before the time. Wherefore whether good men die or liue, it is done for their wealth. But whether the wicked die or liue, it is done for their puniſhment, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſhal they be plagued, &amp; their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhalbe rewarded them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my moſt dearely beloued, take ye ſuch doctrine and comfort to hart &amp; follow the ſame. Flye in good earneſt (by true repentance &amp; amendment) from ſinne wherewith the worlde hath deſerued this horrible plague: And flie by a true vpright faith vnto Gods worde, wherein is the fountaine of life, &amp; the light of men: Then ſhal ye be whole &amp; ſafe from this and other plagues, and ſo liue to the honour of God &amp; wealth of your neighbour, til the appointed time come wherin God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father (in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Chriſt that we be baptiſed in) ſhal ſend for vs out of this miſerable life to his own euerlaſting kingdome: which God graunt vnto vs all,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="direction">
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>How VVife, Children, and</hi> other friendes shalbe comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>the Huſband being</hi> dead.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing nowe that GOD hath called your huſband, father or other good friend out of this miſerie into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ioy, therefore ſhal ye receiue it willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for it is his worke. Repine not therefore at his worke, neither wéepe againſt his will, but commit the cauſe vnto him: take it at his hand, as a fatherly proouing, and ſay with <hi>Job: <hi>God hath giuen vs him, and hath taken him againe, the name of the Lord be bleſſed: as it was the Lords will, ſo is it hapened.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>God almightie will proue you as he did <hi>Iob,</hi> howe yee will behaue your ſelfe, as hee taketh out of your ſight the thing that yee loue: Hee will admitte well ynough that yee bee ſorry. For it is ſeldome ſéene but a man (be hee neuer ſo vile or of ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reputation) hath euer a ſundrie gifte
<pb facs="tcp:17911:23"/> wherewith hee ſerued and profited other. And the ſame gifts were not greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded in a man while he liued: for we regarde little commonly ſuch things as are preſent, but as ſoone as the man is gone, ſo ſoone as the veſſell is ſpilt, then beginne wee to want the gifts that were conteined therein.</p>
            <p>Therefore is it no maruaile, that wee be ſorry for ſuch a gift of God, if it bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of our ſight.</p>
            <p>As long as we vſe men, and the giftes according as they bee ordained of God for our neceſſitie, then doe wee well, and that can God ſuffer well enough: But that we miſuſe them and make an ydoll of them, that cannot God ſuffer. For when wee put our truſt and comfort in man, or any other creature, then doe wee wrong and miſuſe the ſame, and the curſe commeth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs: whereof it is written <hi>Jeremy 17. <hi>Curſed is the man that putteth his truſt in man.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all mans helpe is to be ſuffered on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they be preſent, and that we haue néede of them: but as ſoone as they are gone, then muſt we looke for other helpe, namely: God letting goe it that paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:17911:23"/> thinking it to be temporall, fading at the twinckling of an eye, and vanity that is in this worlde. We haue here no aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thing, but muſt looke about for the thing to come, that endureth for euer.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe doth God draw and pull vs ſo from the creatures. And ſéeing hee is our true father, and bridegrome and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, he can not (for hee is ſtrong and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous) abide that we ſet our hope, loue or truſt vpon any creature. This is the cauſe then that he doeth take vs from them and carieth vs vpon him ſelfe. For looke on what creature wee haue moſt hope, loue and affection, that will he ſooneſt take out of our ſight, if he doth loue vs. And when hee hath ſuch ielouſie vpon vs, then doeth hee moſt chiefly declare his loue towarde vs.</p>
            <p>By this alſo it commeth, that Chriſt <hi>Math.</hi> 18. forbiddeth vs <hi>to call any man father vpon earth, for we haue onely one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen, namely GOD,</hi> which will not, nor can ſuffer vs to call or to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man vpon earth father: &amp; that becauſe wee ſhould depend and hang onely vpon him, looking for all good of him. For he wil be the ſame that we may ſurely truſt vnto:
<pb facs="tcp:17911:24"/> ſéeing he cannot nor will faile vs, and that becauſe he is no earthly but an heauenly father. For this cauſe then is that man bleſſed and happie, that putteth his truſt, hope and confidence in the Lorde, as the Prophet ſayeth.</p>
            <p>Finally, if when nature fulfilleth her courſe, man hath but continuall trauaile &amp; miſerie, &amp; after that this courſe of nature is ended and at reſt, man is eaſed of ſo great trauaile: we ſéeme to hate rather then to loue them that be departed, if wee would wiſh them to be in this wretched world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Moreouer in making ſo much of our friends departed, and ſetting ſo great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vpon them, wiſhing Gods worke not to be fulfilled vpon them: wee blame God in his will and working, as though he knewe not better what were beſt both for them and vs than we.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore ſet our will in Gods will, and ſuffer him to worke at his pleaſure. For he knoweth beſt what is both our friendes, and our ſoules health.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Psalm">
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:24"/>
            <head>A Pſalme to bee ſaid in <hi>the time of ſickeneſſe or any</hi> other aduerſities.</head>
            <p>O Come let vs humble our ſelues, &amp; fall downe before the Lorde with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and feare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For he is the Lord our God: and wee are the people of his paſture, and the ſheepe of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come therefore, let vs turne againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Lord, for he hath ſmitten vs, and he ſhall heale vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs repent &amp; turne from our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: And our ſinnes ſhalbe forgiuen vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs turne, and the Lorde will turne from his heauy wrath, and wil pardon vs, and wee ſhall not perriſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For we acknowledge our faults; and our ſinnes be euer before vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue ſore prouoked thine anger, O Lord: thy wrath is waxed hot, &amp; thy heauy diſpleaſure is ſore kindled againſt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt in thine indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtricke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs with grieuousſicknes: &amp; by &amp; by we haue fallen
<pb facs="tcp:17911:25"/> as leaues beaten downe with a vehement winde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indéede wee acknowledge, that all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments are leſſe then our deſeruings: But yet of thy mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lord correct vs to amendement, and plague vs not to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For thy hand is not ſhortened, that thou canſt not helpe: neither is thy goodneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, that thou wilt not heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou haſt promiſed, O Lorde, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we cry thou wilt heare vs: whileſt we yet ſpeake, thou wilt haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For none that truſt in thee ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: neither any that call vppon thee ſhall be deſpiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For thou art the only Lord, who woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and doeſt heale againe, who killeſt, &amp; reuiueſt, bringeſt euen to hell, and brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt backe againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our fathers hoped in thee: they truſted in thee, and thou diddeſt deliuer them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They called vpon thee, and were hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: they put their truſt in thée, and were not conſounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Lord, rebuke vs not in thine indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: neither chaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in thy heauy diſpleaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:25"/>
            <p>O remember not the ſinnes and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our youth: but according to thy mercie thinke thou vpon vs, O Lord for thy goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs, O Lord, for wee are weake: O Lord heale vs, for our bones are vexed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now in the vexation of our ſpirits, and the anguiſh of our ſoules, we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thee, and wee crie vnto thee: heare Lord, and haue mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For thine owne ſake, and for thy holy names ſake: in cline thine eare, and heare, O mercifull Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For we doe not powre out our prayers before thy face, truſting in our owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, but in thy great and manifolde mercies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Waſh vs throughly from our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and clenſe vs from our ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Turne thy face from our ſinnes: and put out all our miſdéedes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Make vs cleane hearts, O God: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new a right ſpirit within vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Helpe vs, O God of our ſaluation: for the glory of thy name: O deliuer vs, and be merciful vnto our ſinnes for thy names ſake.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>So we that be thy people, and ſheepe of thy paſture, ſhall giue thee thankes for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: and will alwaies be ſhewing foorth thy prayſe, from generation to generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the ſonne and to the holy Ghoſt:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As it was in the beginning, is now and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall be, world without end.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:26"/>
            <head>A Prayer to be vſed at the viſitation of the ſicke.</head>
            <p>O Almightie Lorde and heauenly Father, which haſt promiſed to heare our requeſts, and the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe that aſke of thee in thy Sonne our Sauiour Chriſtes Name, and haſt commaunded vs to pray one for another, we humblie beſéech thée through his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious death and blood-ſhedding, which is the onely attonement for our ſinnes, to bee mercifull to this thy ſicke ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. Forgiue vnto him his ſinnes, O Lord: and increaſe in him ſuch a lyuelie Faith, and féeling of thy fatherly loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him, that all pangues and paines of ſicknes, be they neuer ſo extreame, may ſéeme nothing but thy mercifull and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing calling from theſe worldly miſeries, into the fellowſhip of thy holy ones, whom
<pb facs="tcp:17911:27"/> the more thou louedſt, the more they taſte of afflictions, that béeing throughly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the ruſt of ſinne, they might ſhyne the more gloriouſlie in the kingdom of heauen.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, O mercifull Lord, for that through our frailtie we often doubt whether in extreame paine we may féele our ſelues thy children, or thée our angrie Judge: whereby our Faith is wauering and ſore diſpleaſing vnto thée: we humbly pray thée (if it be thy holy will) to mitigate his torments, and make ſtedfaſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his Faith, that he may with the more quyet minde and aſſured confidence, cry, Abba Father in this life, and after, ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to receaue the crown which thou haſt prepared for them that continue vnto the end. The Lord performe all our petitions through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>Thy mightie arme, O Lord, be ſtill his defender: thy mercie and louing kindneſſe in Ieſus Chriſt thy deare Sonne, his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: thy grace and holy Spirit, his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation, vnto the end, and in the end. So-be-it.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17911:27"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
